<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A Letter from a Presbyterian minister to a member of Parliament</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1693</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 25 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 7 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A48029</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L1429</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R41463</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">31355395</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 31355395</idno>
            <idno type="VID">110440</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A48029)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 110440)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1745:1)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A Letter from a Presbyterian minister to a member of Parliament</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>13 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Edinburgh? :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1693?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Half-title page.</note>
                  <note>Place and date of publication suggested by Wing (2nd ed.)</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: stained, cropped, and with print show-through; slight loss of text.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of Scotland --  Doctrines.</term>
               <term>Presbyterianism --  Scotland.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:110440:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A LETTER FROM A <hi>PRESBYTERIAN MINISTER</hi> TO A MEMBER OF PARLIAMENT.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:110440:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:110440:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>A LETTER FROM A <hi>PRESBYTERIAN MINISTER</hi> TO A MEMBER OF PARLIAMENT.</head>
            <p>YOur Deſire (which has alwayes the force of a Command to me) to give you my Thoughts in Writ, of a Petition given in to His Grace the Duke of <hi>Hamiltoun</hi> His Majeſties High Commiſſioner and the Honourable Eſtates of Parliament, by them who conformed to Epiſcopacy, brings you this Trouble, which a Multitude of my Brethren (were they to undertake the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of this Miſſive, and handle it according to the Grace and Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom which God hath more copiouſly given to them) could have done with more Accuracy of Stile, and more Fully and Nervouſly to the Conviction of theſe Concerned, particularly the Honourable Members of this preſent Parliament, than I am capable to do; yet I have expoſed this Draught to an obſervant Generation, and am wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to bear the Cenſures and Contempt of Many, if I may but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute ſome Light to the Conſciences of ſome Well-meaning, but leſs Diſcerning and Obſervant Friends.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:110440:3"/>
            <p>The Petition, at firſt view, ſeems ſo plauſible, as might chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge Reception from all that love the Advancement of the Great Ends of the Goſpel: And truely if the Petitioners had not bewrayed a want of Candor, unworthy of their Character, in their Addreſs to to the laſt General Aſſembly, in the Terms of a <hi>Formula,</hi> Adjuſted by His Majeſty; to which <hi>Formula</hi> in the Letter they cloſly adhere, but not to His Majeſties Meaning, and the genuine Senſe of the Words as Conſerted for Terms of Communion: The Aſſembly at that time would have made a conſiderable progreſs in laying down ſuch Rules, whereby an effectual Door had been opened for Receiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and Aſſuming into a ſhare of the Government all duely qualified; of which they only were the competent Judges, eſpecially in the firſt inſtance.</p>
            <p>Now that the World, as well as our Friends in Parliament, may underſtand how the late Aſſembly could not without great Unfaith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs to God, the King, their Religion and People, receive the Addreſſers into their Communion; nor will (I hope) this Parliament interpoſe their Authority for that effect, without an antecedent Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Church. I ſhall give an ingenuous Repreſentation <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the Matter of Fact, as that Affair was mannaged before the Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly.</p>
            <p>But leſt I be miſtaken in the following Lines, I muſt Preface a few Things. 1. I would Anathematize in my ſelf, and Condemn in others that Malignant and Cenſorious Zeal that overlooks much Excellence in any, and that envies and diſpiſes all deſerving Services, Gifts and Graces, if not ſeated in, and performed by themſelves, and that makes particular Opinions, Modes, Forms and Humors, <hi>the Main,</hi> or <hi>the Only</hi> Terms of Peace and Concord, and that bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toms the Chriſtian Intereſt, Peace and Welfare of the Churches on any Terms too mean and narrow to ſuſtain them. I ſhall never nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Value nor Vindicat that Zeal which ſhuts out thoſe Characters of the Wiſdom which is from above mentioned in <hi>James</hi> 3.17, 18. <hi>2ly.</hi> I would have no Man think that the Repreſentation of the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſers Behaviour to the General Aſſembly is Levelled againſt all, or the greateſt part of that Way, and leaſt of all againſt many of them
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:110440:3"/>who are in the Exerciſe of their Miniſtry on the North ſide of <hi>Tay'</hi> of whoſe ſoundneſs in the Faith, Piety of Life, and painfulneſs in their Miniſtry, we have ſufficient Documents, but only againſt thoſe whoſe Immoralities, Errors, Non-reſidence when veſted with a Charge, tampering with perſons diſſaffected to the Government, Civil as well as Eccleſiaſtick, and other Enormities hath rendred them contemptible in the Eyes of the people, and uncapable of any Office in a well conſtitute Church. <hi>3ly.</hi> I would have none to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe that the Exceptions of the Presbyterian Miniſters are mainly againſt the <hi>Formula,</hi> which in moſt things coincide with the Act of the General Aſſembly in the year 1690, inſtructing their Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners anent the Reception of ſuch Miniſters into Miniſterial Communion, but againſt their Method of improving it, for it is unconteſtable his Sacred Majeſty (whoſe civil Intereſts are inſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably Complicated, and twiſted with theſe of the True Religion) did certainly intend that thereby. They ſhould give ſufficient Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of the Orthodoxy of their Principles: But when the Aſſembly found it neceſſar (from the pregnant Grounds of Jealouſy Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred by not a few of them who openly taught <hi>Arminian</hi> Doctrines at their Synodical Meetings, and Presbytries without being cenſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: And that Doctor <hi>Monro</hi> a leading man amongſt them offered to Subſcribe the Confeſſion of Faith and Catechiſms as <hi>vinculum pacis,</hi> not <hi>Symbolum fidei:</hi> And withal the <hi>Formula</hi> it ſelf ſeemed a little dubious, and capable of being ſtretched to a ſiniſter Senſe, whereby all ſecurity to our Doctrine was eluded and Evacuat, as will appear afterward from the particular conſideration of the <hi>Formula,</hi> which is the Ground they ſtill ſtand upon) to interrogate them concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their meaning of ſome parts of the Addreſs, how unſatisfactory their Anſwers were I leave to any Judicious and impartial perſon to Judge.</p>
            <p>I ſhall paſs over their Anſwer' to the firſt Interrogator without Diſcanting on it, or drawing theſe Inferences which natively follow from it, but when I have told you the Queſtion which was, if they owned the Authority of the General Aſſembly? I ſhall ſet down their Anſwer in their own Words, and leave you to your own Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marks
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:110440:4"/>and and Animadverſions upon it. The Anſwer then <hi>in ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minis,</hi> was <hi>That they conceive they cannot be oblidged to Anſwer any Questions about any part of the Direction and Addreſs, or to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs their Judgment of the Authority of this General Aſſembly farther then his Majesty hath required them to direct their Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſs thereunto.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But the main Queſtion I was concerned about who am neither of a contracted Charity nor a ſworn Votary to humane Inventions, and I muſt confeſs their ſtingy Anſwer did much trouble me. The Queſtion was, <hi>Whether by their promiſing in that Declaration to ſign the Confeſſion of Faith and Catechiſms they do explicitly avow and cordially and firmly profeſs their belief of the Doctrines therein delivered in oppoſition to the</hi> Popiſh, Socinian, Arminian <hi>and other Tenets, Doctrines and Opinions contrare to, and inconſiſtent with the ſaids Confeſſion and Catechiſms?</hi> Their Anſwer to this Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion given in by them in writ, no doubt after Deliberation, for time was allowed them for that end was, <hi>That they can give no Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication of any point or Article in the ſaid</hi> Formula <hi>and Declaration it being conſerted for them, and ſeen and approven by his Majesty, and that they are ſatisfied in Conſcience to ſign the ſaid</hi> Formula <hi>and Declaration in the words as it now stands, and that they can give no Anſwer, if the whole</hi> Formula <hi>and Declaration ſhould be turned into Questions, and that they conceived the words of the</hi> Formula <hi>and Declaration, are as clear as any they can give by way of Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Committee of the Aſſembly found their firſt Anſwer unſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfactory being ſhifting, and upon the matter a Diſowning, or at leaſt a not Owning of this Aſſembly to be the Lawful General Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly of the Church of <hi>Scotland:</hi> And their aſſerting they cannot be oblidged to Anſwer, does not bear that Candor and Reſpect which they ought to carry to this Aſſembly in ſuch a matter, and ſeems to be inconſiſtent with that Deſire they mention in their Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſs to exerciſe their Miniſtry, in Concurrence with the Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terian Miniſters.</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:110440:4"/>
            <p>Their ſecond Anſwer was alſo declared by the Committee no way ſatisfactory, it being not only a Refuſal to explain what appears un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clear to the Committee in any part of the <hi>Formula</hi> and Declaration, but alſo a Refuſal of what is moſt neceſſar for the ſecurity of the Proteſtant Religion.</p>
            <p>Now let the impartial World conſider what any conſcientious Judicatory upon Earth could have done in ſuch Circumſtances, when with a peremptorineſs very Grievous to ſome of us, they refuſed to give the leſt Satisfaction to any Queſtion concerning their meaning in their <hi>Formula,</hi> nor would the Commiſſioners from the <hi>North,</hi> viz. Mr. <hi>Forbes,</hi> and another, whoſe Name I have forgot (both of them grave and pertinent men) Treat with the Aſſembly for themſelves Perſonally in disjunction from their Conſtituents: Though the Aſſembly declared they would admit of no Proxies in this matter, nor of any who did not Perſonally Compear at this, or ſome other Lawful Judicatory; the Nature of the Addreſs, and what is thereby craved, being ſo perſonal and peculiar to the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſers themſelves. Now could any Men of Conſcience admit of all promiſcuouſly, without the leaſt knowledge of them, or Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony concerning them; yea the Addreſſors themſelves could not read ſome of their Names, being Ciphered, who were their Conſtituents, nor give an Account of the Places where they ſerved and were Miniſters for the time. But that the Aſſembly did moſt ſincerely deſign the Reception of all Worthy Men, is undenyably evident; by what they and inferior Judicatories have already done, I know one Presbytery, where theſe who are already aſſumed are the Plurality, ſo little Jealous or Nice are we in receiving Good Men. And that many more were not aſſumed before this time, proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed not from us, but from the ſtop that was given to the Committee of the Aſſemblies Proceeding in the <hi>North.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But that you may have a full view of the <hi>Formula</hi> or <hi>Teſt</hi> to be Signed by all thoſe who were to be aſſumed, I ſhall here inſert it <hi>Verbatim. I</hi> A. B. <hi>do ſincerely Declare and Promiſe that I will ſubmit to the</hi> Presbyterian <hi>Government of the Church, as it is now by Law eſtabliſhed in this Kingdom under Their Majesties King</hi>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:110440:5"/>William <hi>and Queen</hi> Mary, <hi>by Presbyteries, Provincial Synods, and a General Aſſembly: And that I will as becomes a Miniſter of the Goſpel, Heartily concur with the ſaid Government for the Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſing of Sin and Wickedneſs, the promotion of Piety, and the purging of the Church of all Erroneous and Scandalous Miniſters: And I do further Promiſe, that I will Subſcribe the Confeſſion of Faith now confirmed by Act of Parliament; as containing the Doctrine of the Proteſtant Religion profeſsed in this Kingdom.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now though this may well paſs with Honeſt Men, yet the think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing men of the Aſſembly guided, I hope, by the promiſed unerring Spirit of Grace, ſeriouſly perpending and reflecting upon the <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius</hi> of ſome of thoſe with whom they had to do, (for I dare not ſay but others of them were Sincere in their meaning) who are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lived to be Pragmatick Self-deſigning Men, ſupported by <hi>Some</hi> at a Diſtance, who can be pleaſed with nothing that falls not even with their Sentiments and Ways, and who by all means endeavour to keep them at ſinful Diſtances from Perſons better (perhaps) than themſelves, becauſe their <hi>Schibboleth</hi> is not pronounced by them; and by <hi>Others</hi> at home, who without breach of Charity are <hi>the Trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blers of our</hi> Iſrael, and down right Enemies to the Government, both Civil and Eccleſiaſtick; I ſay the Reverend Aſſembly conſidering this, feared that <hi>latet anguis in herba;</hi> and it being their proper Work to Judge of Confeſſions and Conditions of Communion, they found the Terms of the <hi>Formula</hi> General and Uncertain. And truely it cannot be denied but Ill Men may have a Back-door to go out at in the laſt and principal Clauſe of the <hi>Formula.</hi> For if the <hi>as</hi> Reduplicat the Eſtabliſhment by Act of Parliament and not their own Confeſſion of Faith, there is not the leaſt Security given thereby to our Religion: For I may ſafely not only Subſcribe, but, if I were called to it, Swear the Canons of the Council of <hi>Trent as</hi> the Doctrine of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and the Alcoran <hi>as</hi> the Doctrine of <hi>Mahomet,</hi> tho there were not a Word of Truth in one of them, but not <hi>as</hi> the Articles of my Faith; but This I durſt nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Subſcribe, Say nor Swear, without telling withal that they are not the Articles of my Faith with the ſame Breath I do the other,
<pb facs="tcp:110440:5"/>whatever liberty ſome of their way may take, who are profeſſed <hi>Arminians,</hi> and yet willing to ſubſcribe this <hi>Formula</hi> without any ſuch Declaration.</p>
            <p>But that which moſt of all troubles me (who have been their Advocate not in a Corner, my meaning is, I have with a particular zeal urged the Reception of thoſe into Church Communion, and a ſhare of the Government, the courſe of whoſe Life and Miniſtry demonſtrate them to be <hi>Men of God,</hi> for this is my Teſt by which I would have them tryed; and then though they were <hi>Jure Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no Men</hi> in the point of <hi>Epiſcopacy,</hi> of whom I hear there are but very few, and declared at their joyning with us (as the Famous and Renouned Biſhop <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſher</hi> for Learning and Piety did to ſome of our Baniſhed <hi>Presbyterian</hi> Brethren in <hi>Ireland,</hi> when they chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenged him for allowing, at leaſt complying with ſome of the old Corruptions and Traſh of <hi>Rome</hi>) <hi>hoc facio propter Evangelium,</hi> they ſhould be a thouſand times welcomer to me than thoſe who are moſt liberal in their Profeſſions of Repentance and Signing of Teſts, and yet have skill and cunning enough to wait for every opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, and to improve it for the Subverſion of the Government I ſay that which moſt of all troubles me is the Petition juſt now given into this preſent Parliament, which makes them lyable to the moſt perplexing exceptions that can be made againſt them. For beſide that it was an unkindly thing, unbecoming a true Son of the Church to exhibite a Complaint and Lybel Her as Arbitrary in Her Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſal of their Addreſs, and all this to the High Court of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: In the Pettitory part they ſeem to have forgot themſelves; for though their late <hi>Epiſcopal</hi> Government, was built upon no other Foundation, and advanced by no other Methods then Civil Laws Rigorouſly executed, without any conſequent, far leſs ante<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedent determination of any Church Judicatory: The Honour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Parliament they now apply unto, will certainly abhor that down right groſs <hi>Eraſtianiſm,</hi> the like whereof is not to be found in the World, as it would appear They deſire the Honourable States of Parliament to ſet up, for as I underſtand them, they would have an Independent <hi>Imperium in Imperio,</hi> which cannot miſs in a ſhort
<pb facs="tcp:110440:6"/>time of Iſſue in that which will be everſive of the one, and fatal to both. But do they not well know that our Gracious King and Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament has eſtabliſhed <hi>Presbyterian</hi> Government, as it was in the year 1592. And His Majeſty has given repeated Aſſurances to the Church, That he will inviolably preſerve it all His Life? Do they think then that they will deſtroy what they have Built, and pluck up what they have planted, which agrees ſo well with the Soyl, and wants not its Divine Warrant.</p>
            <p>I am told they are but few who Joyn in this Petition, and moſt of theſe from their Conſciouſneſs to themſelves of their Inſufficien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, Profanity or Heterodoxy, Diſpair of Admiſſion into the Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therhood of the <hi>Presbyterians,</hi> and therefore would climb up to any Window, if ſo be they might have Entrance, and thereby acceſs to their Livings and Stipends, but have no Tenderneſs for our Lords Mediatory Crown, and the Priviledges he has purchaſed and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred upon his Church, which do not in the leaſt interfere with Magiſtrates Prerogatives. For our Learned and Wiſe Parliament know, our Principles aſcribe as much power to them in reference to the Church, as any Wiſe and Pious Magiſtrate will require. We grant the Magiſtrate hath a power, for repairing a broken Church, though not for Conſtituting the frame of its Government, and building ſuch a Fabrick of a Church as he pleaſes. A power for cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling Church Aſſemblies to meet for the Government of the Church, though not a power of hindering them to meet at all; a Power of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fending the True Religion, the Doctrine, Worſhip, Diſcipline and Government of the Church; though not a power to determine con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning theſe things at his pleaſure, a power to concurre by his Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil Sanction with the Determinations of the Church, and confirm their Obligation on his Subjects, tho' not a power to force the Church to follow his Dictats in Things Eccleſiaſtick. And in a Word we grant him all power even in Eccleſiaſticks, that is Cumu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lative to the Churches Advantage, tho we deny him to have any Privative power to the Churches Prejudice, and our Fittedneſs to thir Principles is ſufficiently confirmed, becauſe we could never be driven from them by a Tract of many Years violent Perſecution.</p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:110440:6"/>
            <p>And now becauſe this Seribling of mine may go Abroad, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt others reach the hands of thoſe who are of the Epiſcopal way, I'll gratify a little the frankneſs of my own natural Diſpoſition, and deal roundly with the Epiſcopal Brethren, and their Adherents and Abettors: Only with this precaution, that whatever indiſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion Defects or Miſtakes, what I ſay may be Taxed with, theſe may not be caſten upon my brethren, For I ingenuouſly declare, that by Counſel Knowledge nor Contryvance, they have no acceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to it: And therefore let all theſe be lodged at my own Door, and tho I be ſo tender of my ſelf, as to conceal my Name: Yet I fear the Bluntneſs of the Stile Father it ſelf, and tho I expect to be laſhed with Tongues, as ſometimes perhaps I have been undeſerv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edly; yet in my humble Fitts, the deſire, endeavour and deſign of my Poor Soul is to think as meanly of my ſelf as others can, but ſeldom or never is my mind ſhaken with fear, tho alace other paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions equally dangerous are more predominant in me.</p>
            <p>Let me therefore ask the Brethren and others of that way, What makes you ſtand aloof and keep at ſo great diſtance from Confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity unto the preſent Eſtabliſhment, We who are Presbyterians cannot be ſo unthankful to you, but we muſt acknowledge (and I perſwade my ſelf the late King <hi>James</hi> know it) that theſe of your Holy Order, and Perſwaſion had the moſt Active Chief and pinci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal hand in the late happy Revolution, (Pray let me not be miſtaken it's the Biſhops and others in our neighbour Kingdom of <hi>England</hi> I ſpeak of, for our <hi>Scottiſh</hi> Biſhops gave a moſt ſeaſonable Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of their Loyalty, expreſſing their Deteſtation of the then Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> his coming to <hi>England,</hi> as an unjuſt and unnatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Invaſion ſigned by them all. Of this I crave pardon to be a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrancer to our Parliament and yet I cannot deny but they ought to be excuſed if they be all of a Piece, and make no Bonds to declare (as ſome of them did) theſe wiſhed rather to ſee Popery ſet up in <hi>Scotland</hi> then Presbytry) And tho 'tis not to be doubted, but the Presbyterians in both Kingdoms had good will enough, and were as Active as was poſſible: Yet his preſent Majeſty is more adebted to them for their cordial Reception of him, and cloſs adhereing to
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:110440:7"/>him then for the change that was made, and truely were I in their predicament I would value my party on that head, and improve it. But when I put my thoughts to the Rack to find out why it is they improve not this Advantage, I cannot ſuppoſe it flows from a ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pid careleſſneſs, this may be the caſe of ſuch poor Souls among whom there hath been no Viſion, whoſe idol Shepherds have made them like themſelves without any ſpiritual Senſe: Sometimes I think 'tis Policy their carnal Wiſdom teaching them to ſtand as Spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctators, and when things come to a perfect ſetlement they think to have a ſhare in the Benefit, tho they have nothing at ſtake: In o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers I think it fear leſt their Trade go down, and no wonder tho ſuch Crafts men make an Uproar and cry up their <hi>Diana,</hi> or be content to divide the living Child and make a mixture like the transplanted Nations 2 <hi>King.</hi> 19. Who feared the Lord and ſerved graven Images others fear the Refiners fire and Fullers ſope when the ſons of <hi>Levi</hi> come to be tryed, purified, and purged, but there is no fear that the Ark of God will ſmite any with Emrods and afflict him, unleſs he be a <hi>Philiſtine,</hi> in others 'tis pride affectation of ſingularity, raſh Vows never to conform to Presbytry; and big Expectations of a new Revolution, I would have all ſeparatiſts Examine their Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples by the Touchſtone of the Sanctuary, for in my Life I could never underſtand what could juſtifie ſeparation, but when the Terms of Communion were unlawful.</p>
            <p>And now I crave pardon for my long Letter, and ſhall preſume to give you my Advice while ye are at the Helm of Government, and becauſe I love to offend no Friend to our Cauſe I give it you in the words of the great Apoſtle of the Gentiles, <hi>Let your Moderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on be known to all men, the Lord is at hand.</hi> Which I propoſe as the beſt expedient to prevent Convulſions in Church and State; I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member a ſignificant Sentence of an <hi>Engliſh</hi> man. <hi>Power is a Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quid Subſtance, put it in what Veſſels you will, 'tis apt to run over, Are there not with you, even with you, Sins againſt the Lord your God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I have but two or three words more which I cannot ommit, Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Unity amongſt your ſelves, intertain no enemy in your Boſoms, for one ſecret enemy admitted to your Counſels is more dangerous
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:110440:7"/>then ten Thouſand open and declared enemies: And as ye deſire to proſper and would have God to Bleſs you, fail not by a full clear and incontravertable Act of Parliament (that the preſent Judges may be aſhamed to fly in the face of) to Reſtore and Redintegrat theſe poor broken Sufferers by Forfaultures, Fines, and other wayes for Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience ſake in the Late Times, to whoſe Prayers and theſe of their Predeceſſors, called <hi>Puritans,</hi> who bare the Heat and Burden of the Day, ye owe your Deliverance, it is not Charity but Juſtice to refreſh their Bowels, and that theſe Leeches and Spunges that have ſuckt themſelves full, and raiſed their Fortunes upon their Ruines, be left as dry as they were at firſt, if they would follow my Advice they would reſtore of their own accord what they have unjuſtly pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſed: For it is an uncontroverted Maxim in Divinity, <hi>non tollitur peccatum ni restituatur Oblatum.</hi> But if this be not to be expected of moſt of them; then pray let Juſtice be ſpeeded, that Expences and Attendance upon Law Suits eat not out and exhauſt the Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal in queſtion, and the little Stock that by a providence was hid from their Enemies. But above all my earneſt deſire is, That our Bleſſed LORD were firſt ſet into the full poſſeſſion of His Right, and that His Tabernacle were pitch, before any of the Lots for our own Liberties or Intereſts were drawn; This is that which <hi>David Sware unto the Lord, and Vowed unto the Mighty God of Jacob, ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly I will not come into the Tabernacle of my Houſe: nor go up into my Bed: I will not give ſleep to mine Eyes: or ſlumber to mine Eye-lids: until I find out a place for the Lord: an habitation for the Mighty God of Jacob. Pſal.</hi> 132.2, 3, 4, 5. Now that the Lord may enable you firſt to Faithfulneſs and Thankfulneſs to God, and then to our Saviour and Deliverer under him the Kings moſt Excellent Majeſty (whoſe praiſes without being a plagiary I would but obſcure, but you may read them in their due Elevation in the Sermons publiſhed ſince the Revolution by <hi>Tallitſon, Burnet, Patrick,</hi> and others) and <hi>that our Jeruſalem may be beautiful for ſituation, the the Joy of the whole earth, and God known in her Palaces for a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuge</hi> under the auſpicious Government of our King and Parliament, is the hearty Prayer of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Real Friend and Humble Servant.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
